<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jakub Langr's Blog</title><link href="jakublangr.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.jakublangr.com/feeds/non-technical.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>jakublangr.com/</id><updated>2015-09-14T21:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>...especially about the future</title><link href="jakublangr.com/gjp-part2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-14T21:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Jakub Langr</name></author><id>tag:,2015-09-14:jakublangr.com/gjp-part2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A year has passed since I started to make predictions for this fascinating project run by Philip Tetlock a man that has dedicated about 30 years of his life to understanding geo-political forecasting. Recently the project has ended so I would like to share some insights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, I would love to start with &lt;a href="hello-world.html"&gt;evaluation of my own lessons&lt;/a&gt;: I think that overall I ended up over-correcting for the biases I have read about, which is a fascinating lesson. I already mentioned this the &lt;a href="hello-world.html"&gt;first time I was writing&lt;/a&gt; about Good Judgment Project (GJP). At least based on my rudimentary understanding the calibration and observation, it seems that normally people have the opposite bias and the curve is flipped around the 45 degree line (the picture below is from the report I received from Good Judgment Project).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/calibration_curve.png" alt="(Calibration)" align='right' height='300px' weight='300px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second point about randomness was just due to my un-rigorous understanding of randomness that I think I now understand: the problem is that something is random given a certain distribution (so we cannot make a better guess than the observed distribution for any particular observation). My third lesson about conditional probability still remains fair, which is: it is difficult to make it correctly, but as Philip Tetlock correctly pointed out, this is the way forward, because it allows us to get exactly the probabilities we care about: if we do X what will the world do? (Because we do not care about if Iran will build a nuclear bomb, we want to know IF we do nothing will Iran build a nuclear bomb?) 
sting as the project I have been using much during GJP--but they will "soon" be announcing what they are doing next, but who knows what that will entail. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when the results rolled in they were not too bad, I ended up being the 71st percentile, with my imputed scores dragging me down a little (this was necessary, because you could not answer all the questions, though maybe I also picked questions I understood better). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/mean_brier.png" height='400px' width='800px' align='center' /&gt;
&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/density_imputed_comparison.png" height='400px' width='800px' align='center' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think the overall results were quite decent, but I certainly I have loads to learn! While Philip Tetlock certainly tries to help us mere mortals in the &lt;a href="http://edge.org/conversation/philip_tetlock-edge-master-class-2015-a-short-course-in-superforecasting-class-iii"&gt;the political forecasting by giving us better insight in the Edge online seminar&lt;/a&gt;. I have not watched all of them, but they seem amazing so far! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think what GJP mainly showed me is the power of prediction markets: we can not only &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150813062234/http://www.columbia.edu/~bc2656/GooglePredictionMarketPaper.pdf"&gt;use them in companies to guide our own progress&lt;/a&gt;, but we can also use them to &lt;a href="https://home.inklingmarkets.com/"&gt;get a glimpse into the future like Inkling Markets does&lt;/a&gt; by pooling our predictions together in a crowd-sourcing manner. This last link is particularly interesting, as I feel this has &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; commercial applications if only people cared enough about evidence. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philip Tetlock outlines what are the necessary ingredients of good forecasting and he mentions that the best forecasters tend to be publicly minded software engineers, which is partially supported by the Google information flow study and generally it seems that the more quantitative the subject the better you are likely to be as one political forecasting study finds that the &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150614075429/http://www.hamilton.edu/documents/Analysis-of-Forcast-Accuracy-in-the-Political-Media.pdf"&gt;best forecasters in US politics&lt;/a&gt; "tend to be liberal and not lawyers" (most of the good ones were economist, interestingly). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think there is a potential array of problems: are we not likely to fall into the same illusion as with actual financial markets? E.g. that they are &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; efficient and therefore we should almost blindly trust them (as seems to be the narrative in the Conservative US politics)? Surely, given that we now know that most people are not better at forecasting than random (though this may be because all of the stastically efficient arbitration has already been done in financial markets by the algorithmic hedge funds). I think this is up for discussion, but I would definitely not try to apply them to policy debates blindly &lt;a href="http://squid314.livejournal.com/352406.html"&gt;as some authors do&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prediction markets avoid these problems. There is no question of who the experts are: anyone can invest in a prediction market. There's no question of special interests taking it over; this just distributes free money to more honest investors.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My other problem is that while applications in business are fascinating, the sample sizes with exception of &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; (and data-driven?) companies such as Google, there may always be too small of an interest to make this a useful tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we should just stick to talking to each other for now.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="prediction markets"></category></entry><entry><title>Speaking at European Economic Congress 2015</title><link href="jakublangr.com/eec-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-30T21:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Jakub Langr</name></author><id>tag:,2015-06-30:jakublangr.com/eec-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was recently invited to speak at European Economic Congress in Poland partially thanks to the fact that I was working at Aspen Institute Prague back in the summer of 2011. When I saw the line-up for my panel I was a bit terrified: why should anyone care what I had to say. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/panel.png" alt="Panel line up" align='center'
style="height 30%; width: auto " /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;To Poland!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I arrived at the Katowice airport, there was even a guy standing with my name (laminated!) on it waiting to escort me to the hotel. That freaked me out a little bit. Katowice was an interesting city: marred by Communist rule and somewhat this felt like a journey back in time -- recalling my childhood days in Prague. Poland was noticeably different from Czech Republic, but was eerily similar in some of the functionalist buildings and social interaction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never properly been to Poland before except for the couple of times I have barely crossed the border like when I was climbing &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sn%C4%9B%C5%BEka"&gt;Sněžka&lt;/a&gt;, so it was good to have this opportunity to visit! Unfortunately and perhaps fittingly with the atmosphere of a predominantly communist era city, it was quite cold the entire time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;img src='images/IMG_20150420_175640.jpg' alt='Katowice' style="height: 10%; width: auto"&gt;      
    &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;
        &lt;img src="images/IMG_20150420_103638.jpg" alt="President speaking" style="height: 10%; width: auto"&gt; 
    &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference itself was held in a fabulous newly built Conference Center in the middle of Katowice. It was started off by the then President of Poland Bronisław Komorowski. Despite not being explicitly on the agenda, he started discussing the issue of entrepreneurship quite a lot: the issue of retaining talent, attracting investors and so on. Although there were no concrete plans, I still appreciated this as a very important signal as well as the recognition that entrepreneurship is hard and if we want to succeed we must embrace failure. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic was great because that is one of the topics I am passionate about. I think that it is one of the great equalisers in a society as well as an important skill for anyone to pick up. The trouble with entrepreneurship in Europe though is that the social attitudes it encourages are actively decreasing the pool of potential entrepreneurs. Like the fact that our educational systems does not encourage students to experiment and fail at all: neither in the Czech Republic nor at my University (a top UK university). I am fairly sure that most of my teachers and classmates thought I was incredibly arrogant while I was only trying to follow evidence and best practice from people around the world. It took courage to do that and sure I am sure that as a person I have an incredible amount to work on, perhaps more than most, but I still think that I was politely ignored at best and actively discouraged at worst is indicative of why Europe has no major successful start up to speak of with the &lt;a href="https://www.cbinsights.com/research-unicorn-companies"&gt;possible exception of Spotify&lt;/a&gt;. Whilst there is just about &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2015/dec/06/europe-google-silicon-valley-digital-industry"&gt;hundred&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.gpbullhound.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/GP-Bullhound-Research-Billion-Dollar-Companies-2015.pdf"&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2015-06-16/europe-s-tech-unicorns-are-so-tame"&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://arcticstartup.com/opinions/europe-needs-bolder-tech-investments/"&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt; why this is the case, this one is rarely discussed but I think no less important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mainly talk about digital entrepreneurship, because that is where most of my expertise comes from but I think that ultimately, this should generalise to most areas. While I value greatly that the policy makers have taken on such an challenging topic, I have to highlight that the absence of anyone except old white men among the attendees and the whole spirit of the conference was very much in the style of a conference for them, thereby missing almost the entire population and I really hope that business is more inclusive that that. Or at the very least it should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of discussion, obviously, I was not expecting something like &lt;a href="/web-summit-dublin-14.html"&gt;my experience at Web Summit Dublin&lt;/a&gt;, which specialises on tech entrepreneurship, but there was also a massive disconnect between a lot of people were saying and what really needed to happen. Which is a shame, because I think that there is so much direct and obvious stuff that the policy makers could do to ease entrepreneurs' lives: less bureaucracy, encouraging educational system that rewards experiments and reasonable welfare state that does not make failure too costly.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Panel! (SLightly egostistical pictures, don't judge me)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td &gt;
        &lt;img src='images/240627_940.jpg' alt='Panel 3' style="height: 45%; width: auto "&gt;       
    &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td &gt;
        &lt;img src="images/240621_940.jpg" alt="Panel 2" style="height: 45%; width: auto" &gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src='images/20150421_102200.jpg' alt='Panel 1' style="height: 45%; width: auto "&gt;      
&lt;br &gt;
&lt;img src="images/20150421_102129.jpg" alt="Panel 4" style="height: 45%; width: auto "&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br &gt; 
Source of images: PTWP SA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the typical platitudes were then repeated during my panel discussion: how it would be so great to have more European entrepreneurship, young people should do it (which is also not true: anyone has a shot!) and why do all the smart people go abroad? Unfortunately, the reality that it is often too costly financially and socially (also in terms of exit options) to create a new company in Europe and the real issues were sometimes completely missing. On the plus side, during the discussion I got a few shout-outs from others such as "As the gentleman on the far-right [of the panel] noted--without alluding to his political views--the young need to be willing to fail", as mentioned by the German ambassador. Though I was the only one to laugh at that remark, which was quite embarrassing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, I think that it was great that we discussed this topic at all, but I think that Europe--if it is serious about entrepreneurship--needs to examine systematic causes and start doing rather than merely talk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, though, I had a great time in Poland. I think I still learnt loads from this conference and I had an opportunity to have a drink with some of my great former colleagues from Aspen!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="entrepreneurship"></category></entry><entry><title>Web Summit Dublin 2014</title><link href="jakublangr.com/web-summit-dublin-14.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-14T20:00:00+00:00</published><author><name>Jakub Langr</name></author><id>tag:,2014-11-14:jakublangr.com/web-summit-dublin-14.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I rarely get this emotional about an event, but Web Summit definitely is an experience I will never forget. I was incredibly lucky to be &lt;a href="http://blog.websummit.net/student-blog-announcement/"&gt;selected as one of the 22 initial Student Scholars&lt;/a&gt; to give free attendance to Web Summit Dublin 2014. When I was applying little did I know how awesome this experience will be. When they told us that we were selected out of 6,600 applicants (final figure was apparently at 15,000 for all rounds), I was a bit skeptical. When I saw the list of people I was supposed to be going to the Summit with, my only thought was: "I don't belong here".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once it got to term time I did not quite have the brain capacity to worry about this. But somehow, when it eventually got to the Summit itself, I was not sure what to expect. I did not know anyone from the group of scholars and even the arrangements from the Summit with regards to our arrival were very much in the start up mentality -- hectic and required some figuring out. (That is not to blame the team at all, everything that was supposed to work, worked.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My 2 am bus ride to catch my 6 am flight was somewhat annoying, but hey, if it is to go such an amazing event, why not. Actually, it feels kind of boring to travel during regular hours. Already on the bus to the hotel, I met up with two other scholars and I immediately felt at home: super interesting people one of whom went to business school the other to medical school. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the first day we did some serious sightseeing with those who arrived a bit early, as the first event was in the evening. Some people really wanted to go on the Hop On, Hop Off bus tour, which I though was quite touristy, but felt like I should try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-03%2013.55.12.jpg" target="_blank"&gt; &lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-03%2013.55.12.jpg" alt="Excited tourists" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-03%2013.10.56.jpg" target="_blank"&gt; &lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-03%2013.10.56.jpg" alt="Yay bus tour!" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Definitely no regrets, we got to see a lot of Dublin that we normally would not have any time to see. Then it was time for our first pub crawl. These were integrated into Web Summit and there was even a special pub crawl for the scholars with some of the more successful companies at the Summit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes as no surprise that the networking was awesome. But what is far more important: it felt really natural. I always hated networking for the sake of networking. I wanted to meet new people and make friends. And if they happen to be useful connections, great. If not, it's still a win, you have an awesome friend. That is really what made it so easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we were escorted to dinner at Guinness factory, where on the top floor some speakers (Drew Houston!!!) along with scholars were all having dinner. I think I even shook Drew's hand so that already made me quite happy. Plus I just casually happened to speak to the CEO of Idea Paint. Incredible. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the dinner we moved to the Night Summit, which was a street rented out by Web Summit so that the attendees of the Summit can wind down and talk to each other over a pint. I think I came home at about 2 or 3 am. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/IMAG0803.jpg" target="_blank"&gt; &lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/IMAG0803.jpg" alt="Guiness Dinner with Drew et al" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-04%2008.42.05.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-04%2008.42.05.jpg" alt="Yay start up exhibition hall!" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, it was start of the Summit's main part, which was absolutely &lt;em&gt;mind-blowing&lt;/em&gt;. So many awesome start-ups to talk to, the picture above only barely describe my excitement when I saw the main exhibition hall. But also, there were about seven stages that were full of the super stars of tech community: Tim O'Reilly (sorry for the bad picture), Peter Thiel (I missed the book signing :( ), GitHub CTO and many others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2013.23.04.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2013.23.04.jpg" alt="Tim O'Reilly" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2016.35.56.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2016.35.56.jpg" alt="Peter Thiel" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Night Summit made me happy to be missing sleep again. But we went to have drinks at the Lord Mayor of Dublin, which was amazing. Though at that time I was already spoiled, as earlier in the day we saw an opening of NASDAQ from Dublin by the Prime Minister of Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-04%2014.21.16.jpg" source="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-04%2014.21.16.jpg" alt="NASDAQ Opening. NBD." align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-04%2018.18.52.jpg" source="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-04%2018.18.52.jpg" alt="Lord Mayor of Dublin" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the last day had so much to offer: Bono, Dana Burnetti and many others. Paddy Cosgrave the main organizer handled everything excellently, though he was pointing out the issues with WiFi and how that is not really their fault a bit too often. (Though to me that did not pose a problem.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2017.19.28.jpg" target="_blank"&gt; &lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2017.19.28.jpg" alt="Bono et al" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2017.01.49.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2017.01.49.jpg" alt="Dana Burnetti" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was also a week full of incredible occurrences: I randomly happened to speak to the founder of Twitch, without even knowing. One other scholar was just finishing his homework in the lobby of our hotel and happened to stumble upon Dave McClure -- the founder of 500 Start-ups -- the person who just a day earlier said on stage: "If you are going to pitch to my f*cking face [without being invited to], I am not going to listen to you". But at this time Dave was trying to set-up Node.js (&lt;a href="hack-zurich-14.html"&gt;framework that we all love&lt;/a&gt;) and my fellow scholar who happened to know Node got an internship offer for this one act of kindness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-05%2022.33.40.jpg" target="_blank"&gt; &lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-05%2022.33.40.jpg" alt="The Kooks!" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2014.51.41.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/2014-11-06%2014.51.41.jpg" alt="Dave McClure" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other story that I still struggle to believe is that the Kooks happened to be playing without many people even knowing about it in one of the Night Summit venues. I only found out about that less than an hour before the show from a friend of mine when we just happened to be randomly talking about what we are doing tonight. He forwarded me an email (that already was forwarded at least 5 times) that was saying that Kooks will be playing in one of the venues. I don't think that it was that the organizers were trying to hide this event -- it's just that so much else awesome was going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, words cannot describe how amazing this event was. I have learned so much from other Summit attendees, especially the scholars. I have had many interesting, fun and inspiring conversations. So if you are still in university, keep an eye out! Organizers promised they will do it again next year and you don't want to miss that!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Web Summit"></category><category term="non-technical"></category><category term="Dublin"></category><category term="Start-up"></category></entry><entry><title>#hackZurich 2014: A hackhathon to remember</title><link href="jakublangr.com/hack-zurich-14.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-10-12T20:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Jakub Langr</name></author><id>tag:,2014-10-12:jakublangr.com/hack-zurich-14.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When you work with a lot of engineers, you start to envy all those cool personal projects they have and all those cryptic plug-ins they know and have mastered. A lot of this happened at Hackathons. So I wanted to try one myself to have a proper experience of trying to code up an app from scratch in less than 42 hours. So when I found about hackZurich, I was sold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all seriousness, I was. The hackathon looked &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;: more sponsors than any society or event I've seen. Cool APIs opened only for hackZurich and &lt;em&gt;they even reimbursed most of travel costs.&lt;/em&gt; The only annoying this was that this event was happening around exam time. But seeing as I am writing elaborate odes on this, you can probably guess what I chose. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except it was not that easy: I knew I wanted to go to a hackathon, except I've never been before. And there was an application process. Realistically, I am not sure how selective it was, but there was a cap of 300 people and given that there are always freebies and free food, I think hackathons can be quite appealing.... at least for me. But I mean we had to sleep on the ground, on the tables and on our bags and some people did not even have sleeping bags. I do not want it to sounds like I am complaining. No one actually slept a whole lot (I slept about 4 hours first night and one hour the second) so no one really cared. I found my own non-lit corridor and slept on the floor, because I really need quiet environment. But hey! It was a fun experience and I was worried I am getting a little snobby. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So hacking! We had about 30-40 hours to code an app on any topic, but noting of course that some companies gave us exclusive (and some promoted only their existing) &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Application_programming_interface"&gt;APIs&lt;/a&gt; for us to try something new. Except, as a person knowledgeable mostly of the data science stack, I soon realized that I will need to go back to coding some web apps to have something to show. That, however, was a problem, because I have not coded up a web app in over a year. So I was afraid that I simply may not be up to the challenge skill-set wise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, organizers created a Facebook group for people to get together and discuss their preliminary ideas, but standard hackathon rules apply: no code before the official kick-off. So I joined the group and was discussing ideas with people and was quite happy to see that a lot of people were not extremely concerned about the lack of specific skills. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this, I was quite nervous, because this was my first hackathon and I was not quite sure what to expect. I teamed up with a friend of mine, because I figured going to a hackathon in a different country in a busy period and coding in technologies I have never mastered and even the little experience I had was long time ago, it is going to be challenging as is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We roughly discussed the idea beforehand, but as my head was full of Mathematical Methods exam that I was supposed to be taking the day before leaving, I did not quite do justice to preparation as a lot of Node JS I needed to refresh on the go and that slowed me down considerably. But let's not jump the gun. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finishing my exam on Thursday and doing chores until my departure from Oxford shortly after noon, I was quite freaked out: I still haven't really unpacked and I was already going places. But the trip was cool: I was flying from London City Airport for the first time, which was quite exiting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/IMAG0752.jpg" alt="Destination: #hackZurich" align="center" style="width: 620px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite not knowing anything about Zurich, I perfectly navigated and caught the pre-planned (from about a week ago!) train straight to the hackathon venue, which made my day. Hackathon itself was held at a &lt;a href="http://technopark.ch"&gt;TechnoPark&lt;/a&gt;, which seemed to be a quite modern open space for start-ups and small companies. Upon arrival, I got my badge and bag of goodies that I still haven't fully explored, because there's just &lt;em&gt;so much stuff.&lt;/em&gt;  (Yay!) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I unfortunately missed the opening ceremony, but I arrived just in time for the pretty cool workshops: Evernote had an introduction to their APIs and Software Development Kits and then I went to presentation about Google wearables. Where Google-certified android master (presenter) sent a guy who wanted to go to the Apple workshop to the 6th floor (where there was no workshop) and after the poor guy left, he said: "Ooops, I must have been using Apple Maps." The sass is strong with this one. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the workshops, &lt;strong&gt;let the hacking commence.&lt;/strong&gt; My friend and I were using MEAN stack and &lt;a href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;D3.JS&lt;/a&gt; to build a budget tracking app. That is &lt;a href="http://mongodb.org"&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://expressjs.com/"&gt;Express.JS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://angularjs.org/"&gt;Angular.JS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://nodejs.org/"&gt;Node.JS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was challenging doing all this coding, but I have to say, quite fun. The atmosphere was amazing and a ton of caffeinated drinks around. Here and there was an occasional food shortage, but hey: free food. After the kick-off people, obviously, started coding. And they coded... until 430 am. At which point I decided that it &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be a good idea to get some rest and so I finally managed to find a nice hallway to sleep in by about 5 am. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://scontent-a.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xpa1/v/t1.0-9/s720x720/10689898_10203303761088371_4719824619037743016_n.jpg?oh=e9683900216a3692b0ca916a2be2f27c&amp;oe=54AE910E" align="center" alt="4 am #hackZurich" style="width: 620px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You think that was bad? Check out where some of these poor souls have been sleeping:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BztdrGDCEAMmoY6.jpg:large" align="center" style="width: 620px;" alt="People sleeping on the floor."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/IMAG0772.jpg" alt="Finders, sleepers" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/IMAG0777.jpg" alt="Finders, sleepers" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite my effort to stow myself away I was woken up several times by people sneaking through my corridor to find an even more obscure corridor to sleep in, which sometimes looked quite weird, not to mention awkward, especially if you make eye contact. Anyways, I woke up by 8:30 am to sounds of some radio (&lt;strong&gt;rage&lt;/strong&gt;) and since I was up and I got breakfast and started working. Morning was quite productive, but after a while we got quite tired and hungry and so we went on a walking tour of Zurich that organizers kindly organized for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/IMAG0762.jpg" alt="Finders, sleepers" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;td&gt;1
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/IMAG0765.jpg" alt="Finders, sleepers" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/IMAG0767.jpg" alt="Finders, sleepers" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;td&gt;1
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/30848031/blog/IMAG0771.jpg" alt="Finders, sleepers" align="right" style="width: 310px;"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say Zurich is quite an amazing city. It has a very picturesque, small-town feel and it really feels too fairly-taily to be true.  &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next night was a bit more rough as we had issues with our database and Node.JS not being synchronized, which is one of the pains of working with asynchronous stacks, which took us quite a long time to fix. I stopped working at around 4:30 and got up at 6 something to go finish our app before the 930 am deadline.  &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, our app did not make it into finals--as those were only for 1/4 of the participants--but this hackathon was definitely awesome. Would do again.  &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing as I yammered for too long again, I will leave it at that, but I will be back for more!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="non-technical"></category></entry></feed>